<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-17T21:39:15+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Geowanderer</title><subtitle>Blog from an Earth wanderer. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Talking to animals</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/talking_to_animals/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Talking to animals"/><published>2024-09-09T02:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-09T02:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/talking_to_animals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/talking_to_animals/"><![CDATA[<p>I was laying in bed yesterday, enjoying the tranquillity and the warmth of the last summer days, when the gentle buzz of a moth came and ruined my peace. It made several turns in the air, some twenty centimetres right above my head, teasing me until I had to get up and shoo it away.</p> <p>How nice it would be if we could actually talk to animals! I wondered, as I was back on the bed again, five minutes later, recovering from this incidence. That way, we could just tell the insects and moths: we mean no harm, but please don’t get too close to our territory, and keep several decimetres from our beds. I could tell the friendly neighbourhood spiders to move to the corner near the window, where it could be best fed by the incoming insects from the outside, while not disturbing me in my daily routines. I could tell the birds trapped in the staircases where the exit is, so that they wouldn’t need to hit the glass in vain. People could actually communicate with their pets. That sounds like an amazing idea!</p> <p>But then if that is the case, how are people going to kill the animals, with whom we can communicate? How are farmers going to handle the situation, where they are sending the animals they have been talking to since their childhood to butchers? And how are butchers going to butcher the talking animals? I begin to sense there is a ration behind there being both talking and non-talking animals in <em>Narnia</em>. It would be very weird to domesticate, cultivate in batch and then butcher in batch the animals if people can talk to them. There will be no more Geschnetzeltes, Schnitzel, goulash, beef stroganoff, Peking duck, meat skewers, or any animal products that require animal husbandry. Pigs will say: please don’t butcher me, we had such good time together, didn’t we? Cows will say: you are pressing on my breasts too hard. That would be a really weird world.</p> <p>Hunting / gathering might still work. Cannibalism is possible in human societies, so apparently people is still capable of eating animals with which they can talk and communicate. If people fish from the sea and obtain fishes that are half dead any way after being brought away from the water, they could probably bring themselves to consuming them. But raising animals and then butchering them? It would be establishing relationships with these talking animals only to kill them in the end. That is probably unseen in human history, unparalleled by cannibalism or slavery. The agriculture centred around animal meat and animal products just doesn’t work - and neither does the industry that relies on these materials.</p> <p>The only option, diet wise, is probably to take up a vegan lifestyle. But if that had always been the case in human history, would our civilisation still reach its current status? How much more effort would it be for people to grow crops if they couldn’t bring themselves to enslaving cows? And what if at some point, enlightened human beings and cows decide to abolish this slavery? How much longer would it take for people to develop the agricultural technologies, without the use of talking animals? Sometimes it is just better to leave the stone unturned, better not to look under the carpet, much like it is much better and easier for people to not look at the history of slavery, colonisation, and the exploitation on the developing and under-developed countries, because these very facts undermine the entire history, and leaves the entire current situation in an unjustifiable and undefendable status.</p> <p>Or maybe, from a more technically possible point of view, being able to communicate with animals does not really mean that we can talk to animals in the same way we talk to each other human beings. I began to realise this, as the more sensible part of me got the upper hand. The “languages”, if any, are certainly different! Barks, roars, gestures, and hormones - complicated as these may be, can these really contain as high bandwidth as human language? And if zoologists and biologists are correct in saying that dogs can be as smart as three-year-old children, they also mean that many other animals are not. Even if we have the technology for interfacing the different communication systems, talking to animals whose communication bandwidth is far lower than our language, and/or whose information processing speed is far lower than human beings, will be an upsetting experience. It would be like a modern desktop CPU talking directly to a vintage hard drive. Data transfer from an SSD to a floppy disk. Or, as said in <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11680642/">Pantheon</a>, uploaded intelligence communicating with real humans. Even the artificial intelligence nowadays, if they somehow obtain actual consciousness, must find interfacing with human an unbearable experience. If I couldn’t even tell my six-year-old nephew to stop shooting me with his toy gun, how am I supposed to tell the moths, which are orders of magnitudes less intelligent than dogs, which are less intelligent than my nephew, to understand “I mean no harm, but please don’t get too close to my bed”?</p> <p>It seems to me that talking to animals, even if possible, would be fundamentally different from talking to a human being. I wouldn’t be able to easily make moths understand that I would prefer to be kept quiet, or make spiders understand constructing nets too close to my desk or bed would only result in more casualties and unnecessary destructions - both for them and for me. But hey, on the bright side, I guess it would also mean that the evolution of human civilisation would not be severely changed by whether we can talk to animals or not! There will still be Geschnetzeltes, Schnitzel, goulash, beef stroganoff, Peking duck, and meat skewers. Satisfied with this conclusion, I closed my eyes again, and fell back into the tranquil state.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What would it be like, if human beings can talk to animals?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s a Schnitzel on a stick</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/schnitzel_stick/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It’s a Schnitzel on a stick"/><published>2024-05-21T02:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-21T02:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/schnitzel_stick</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/schnitzel_stick/"><![CDATA[<p>In the <del>celebrated and acclaimed</del> (I seem to be the only one celebrating and acclaiming) cartoon film <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0443536/?ref_=ext_shr_lnk">Hoodwinked!</a> from 2005, one of the main characters, the Woodsman, drives a Schnitzel truck which serves “Schnitzel on a stick”.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9"> <iframe class="embed-responsive-item w-100" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tlhaqz7zfJo?si=zinIAO_TM3UDiP3S" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""> </iframe> </div> </div> </div> <p><br/></p> <p><em>To miss this dream will make me sick</em><br/> <em>But for now I serve the Schnitzel stick!</em><br/> Says the man who dreams of becoming part of a Yodelling group or an actor, but can only get the role of a Woodsman in the commercial, and has to serve Schnitzels on a stick for a living.</p> <p>But what exactly is <strong>a Schnitzel on a stick</strong>? This idea is rejected by Tobi (and pretty much everyone in our research group). To them, Schnitzel on a stick is as much as a heresy as: pineapples on a pizza, ketchup on pasta, and (to very selected people) Nutella inside a croissant. To show that it is a thing, I managed to find a Schnitzel truck from Texas that actually serves Schnitzel on a stick:</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9"> <iframe class="embed-responsive-item w-100" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IRqj69KK6MY?si=Jyg_kX7SWmkAnNJZ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""> </iframe> </div> </div> </div> <p><br/></p> <p>Apparently, the Schnitzel on a stick has mostly the same topology as a regular Schnitzel (not meatballs or separated pieces of meat on a skewer), only with a wavy pattern and is pierced by a stick. The same owner of the Schnitzel truck also provides the recipe for making your Schnitzel on a stick!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <div class="embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9"> <iframe class="embed-responsive-item w-100" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/j5HowM2CWhU?si=JmpkBWaGfPuPFq2m" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""> </iframe> </div> </div> </div> <p><br/></p> <p>Now everyone can make their own Schnitzel on a stick at home!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Culture"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In hoodwinked, the nette Schnitzelmann sells Schnitzel on a stick. Is it a legitimate form of Schnitzel?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">当聚会在野草边</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/wild_grass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="当聚会在野草边"/><published>2024-02-05T02:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T02:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/wild_grass</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2024/wild_grass/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>草在结它的种子，风在摇它的叶子。我们站着，不说话，就十分美好。</p> <p>——顾城《门前》</p> </blockquote> <p>草在结它的种子。掩映在层层叠叠的草木之下，薪火相传的种子无声地生长着、壮大着，一点点饱满起来，为新一年的传宗接代做好准备。冬令时分的草原，草本的地上部分将会悉数枯萎，留下那在种皮中蛰伏的生机。间隔着树林的草地中央，穿流而过的是一条水流平缓的河流，倒映出草地之畔茂盛的树木，以及遥远的天际线处，衬着湛蓝天空的山峦。</p> <p>白须老者坐在草地上一棵略显孤单的椿树下，手边放着一个硕大的葫芦。椿树庞大繁茂的枝叶笼罩着一方绿荫；穿过树林的风吹过，它摇曳着，晃动着，发出沙沙的声响。白须老者笑了，他红润的面庞上浮现出孩童般的开怀，引起涟漪似的皱纹。他轻轻地把脑袋倚靠在树干上，引得椿树又一阵摇晃，然后伸展开光脚，惬意地半躺下，端过前日在树林那头村子里取来的瓜，一把砸开，放在草地上用手掰着吃了起来。</p> <p>沿着远处的河流走来了一个灰发老者。他鲜艳的衣衫已显得有些凌乱，高耸的帽子下，灰发错杂地涌出来，参差地覆盖着皱纹像黄土塬一样深重的脸庞。他仰着头，眉头虬结，双手紧攥，口中念念有词：</p> <p>“入溆浦余儃徊兮，迷不知吾所如。深林杳以冥冥兮，乃猿狖之所居。山峻高以蔽日兮，下幽晦以多雨。霰雪纷其无垠兮，云霏霏而承宇。”</p> <p>灰发老者说话间，走到了白须老者面前。他几乎是忿怒地瞪着白须老者，因为后者正逗乐了似的望着他。回神过来，他又瞥见了周遭土地上疯长的野草；这似乎成了浇在火上的油。灰发老者跺起脚，气急败坏地摆手道：</p> <p>“鸾鸟凤凰，日以远兮。燕雀乌鹊，朝堂坛兮。露申辛夷，死林薄兮。腥臊并御，芳不得薄兮。阴阳易位，时不当兮。怀信侘傺，忽乎吾将行兮？”说罢，灰发老者泪落，他瞪着泪眼朦胧的双眼愤怒地看着疯长的野草，苦难深重的样子。白须老者边大口啃咬着手中的瓜，边递过去一片，示意灰发老者也吃。但是灰发老者却仿佛没看见似的；他漠然地推开白须老者递来的瓜，边注视着野草愣愣地发呆。</p> <p>“你不吃吗？”白须老者嘲讽似的问道，“看起来你很厌恶那些野草。”</p> <p>灰发老者沉默了片刻，然后转向了白须老者：”你难道看不出这个世界已经腐败了吗？菊花在杂草的环境中枯萎，露申在一枝黄的包围中死亡。庸人与庸才包围着有才之士，抢夺着有肥力的土壤，占有着充满阳光的空气，而我们则被包围在污秽的环境中。这就是逐渐走向萎靡的自然，这就是逐渐走向堕落的世界，因为这些杂乱的野草，这些肮脏的种！“</p> <p>白须老者哂笑着。他放下手中的瓜果，在野草上擦拭了一下沾着汁水的手，然后发问了：</p> <p>“你怎么看待树林那头的草地呢？”</p> <p>“平庸的无用之种。”</p> <p>“这种野草呢？”</p> <p>“毒害的邪恶之种。”</p> <p>“所以你喜欢菊花？有芳香的草本？蕙兰？”</p> <p>“余既滋兰之九畹兮，又樹蕙之百畮。扈江离与辟芷兮，纫秋兰以为佩。朝饮木兰之坠露兮，夕餐秋菊之落英。”</p> <p>“是这样吗？”白须老者审视着灰发老者，“菊、兰、蕙、露申、辛夷，果真就好吗？你的好恶，难道等同于天地的好恶吗？树林那头的草地，是牛羊的牧场，你眼中的无用，却是滋养牛羊的食粮；这些野草，是草地的佑护者，你眼中的毒害，却是庇佑草地中小生物的巨伞、昆虫的粮食，何毒之有？而反倒是你最喜欢的芳草，既不是牲畜的食粮，又不是昆虫的保护伞，只有蜜蜂与蝴蝶才与你一同喜爱他们。你崇尚你的理想，却在与现实的对抗中越陷越深，然天下本无恒定的对错是非，何必以己之喜好求同于世间万物？”</p> <p>“我不信，”灰发老者道，“我不信这个邪。你只是被这个世道一并毒害，方才出此妄言。你看看你的身边吧，愚昧的人！”他指了指椿树，“这棵椿树，枝干疏松，摇摆不定，如何能有一日成可用之材？那破葫芦，”他又指着地上的葫芦，“空具躯壳，轻飘飘而脆弱，盛水都会破裂，如何有用武之地？这是欺骗自己，在污秽中告诉自己很快乐！”</p> <p>“你又不是鱼，怎么知道污秽的水中鱼有没有自得其乐？”白须老者平静地说，“大樗，没错，它不结实，造不了房子，但它庞大的树荫却可以提供乘凉的处所；大瓠，没错，它很脆弱，盛不了水，但它密度小才可以送你渡河。”说罢，他拿起葫芦，递给灰发老者。</p> <p>然而灰发老者并不领情，他头也不回地走向河流：</p> <p>“快回去，蠢材！新浴之人，必振衣、弹冠，想要周身没有尘秽。我又如何能与你为伍，用你的东西，和这个肮脏的世界共度一生？余将董道而不豫兮，固将重昏而终身！”</p> <p>水波的一丝涟漪吞没了灰发老者的身躯。在悠悠流逝的河水中，他的生命就这样结束。河岸上，白须老者击着大腿唱着歌：“沧浪之水清兮，可以濯我缨；沧浪之水浊兮，可以濯我足。”然后，他拿起未尽的瓜，继续享用。</p> <p><br/></p> <p>入夜了，白须老者用椿树的树枝架起一个小架子，升起一小丛火，而后从树后扯出一只拔了毛的鸡，小心翼翼架在火上烤了起来。少顷，最外面的鸡皮已经渗出汁水，一丝香气袅袅升起。白须老者耐心地看着，脸上浮现出期待的微笑。</p> <p>沿着远处的河岸走来一个年轻人。他戴着白色的高帽，白皙的脸庞上有着一双充满好奇而脆弱的眼睛，脸上挂着和善温柔的神情；他身着单薄的衬衫，恰恰适合暖和的夏夜。见到人，他的脸蓦地亮了起来。他快步向白须老者走去，脚下充沛着欢脱。“嗨！”他欢快地叫道，“嗨！真高兴能在这儿见到人影！”</p> <p>白须老者也非常高兴。他指着剩下的半个瓜：“来一点吧？”又努嘴示意那只烤鸡，“烤好以后一起吃吧！”年轻人开怀地坐下，拾起地上的瓜，掰下一瓣开始享用。夏日夜晚，微风拂过，吹动着孕育着新生的野草。年轻人若有所思的样子，他脸上涌现出一丝欣慰，随即又是无奈。</p> <p>“这样的生活已经很难得了，”年轻人回过神来，注视着白须老者，“现在买个果子，买个瓜，买只鸡，都不容易。真不容易还能在这里体会生活的乐趣。你瞧啊，草在结它的种子，风在摇它的叶子，我们不说话，只要坐着，就十分美好。”</p> <p>老者露出困惑的神情，“为什么很困难呢？难道不是想做就能做的吗？”</p> <p>“曾经是这样的，”年轻人脸上掠过一丝阴影，“但现在不同了。书不好再读了，钱没法再挣了，买东西也不同了……我不知道错和对、正确和谬误在哪里分家，这不是内心所为，却是环境所致。因为你瞧，夜幕已经降临了。在人群聚集的地方，大家都在传唱没有声音的歌谣。恐惧笼罩着黑夜，爱与恨在恐惧的獠牙下滋生潜伏。人与人的关系就像——”</p> <p><em>（“异乎寻常的亲族，漠不相关的路人。”）</em></p> <p>“我已经走了很远，”年轻人继续道，他的脸色愈加沉重了，“从几百里外一路走来，走了那么远，就是为了寻找一把火、一盏灯，任何可以照彻黑暗的亮光。现在，我终于找到了这里，这些许美好的事物：光、热，食物，轻松的氛围。但是，早晨依然没有来临，人们的记忆依然透不过一丝亮光。”</p> <p>白须老者沉默着。半晌，他发话了：</p> <p>“也许黑夜，总是必然的经过。有昼就会有夜，有晨就会有昏。这是痛苦的，是闭塞的，是令人恐惧的，但是夜也好、晨也罢，在这背后主宰着变化的，都是颠扑不破的自然规律——”</p> <p>“所以呢？”年轻人面有愠色，“你是在与我讲：这黑暗无害，不用抗拒？”</p> <p>“不，不是，”老者沉吟道，“在任何环境下，总有对应的人的态度；这些都是规律的一部分，这是所谓的真君。圣人不凝滞于物，与其在黑暗的痛苦中折磨自己，终了一生，不如寓之于庸，在平凡中蛰伏与等待，接受黑夜存在的事实，同时期待到来的光明。这也不失为一种态度呀？”</p> <p>“噢，”一抹讥笑挂上了年轻人的嘴角，“隐匿锋芒，隐匿真知？感谢上苍，你真是和传唱着寂静之歌，在黑暗中对着夜空顶礼膜拜的人们一模一样。我本来期许我在这里能找到了慰藉，可是我们不同。我是个任性的孩子，被幻想宠坏的孩子。我有理想，我有忿怒，我无法继续在黑夜里等待美好又灿烂的早晨。”年轻人站起身来，他庄严的脸庞在火光映照下犹如一尊铜像。慢慢地，他从口袋里掏出一把手枪。</p> <p>“你要做什么？”白须老者警觉起来。</p> <p>一声枪响划破了黑夜的寂静，污红的血液洒在野草上。年轻人逐渐苍白的面庞上两行无声的泪，成了他告别黑夜，也告别世界最后的书信。</p> <p><br/></p> <p>晨星划过了漆黑的夜空。东方隐隐泛白，一抹紫红色的朝霞染上了黎明群青的天空。睡梦中，老者翻了个身。在远处树林外隐约传来的鸡鸣声中，他的意识逐渐清晰起来，眼皮翕张地动弹了几下，然后蓦地张开了。他的脸色亮了起来，支撑着爬了起来。此时东方既白，初生的日头褪去了稚嫩的红光，换上了明亮的黄色。</p> <p>昨日吃剩的烤鸡残骸还悬在架子上。椿树旁搁放着一具尸体，那是昨晚年轻人留下的。白须老者叹了口气，然后将年轻人的尸身推入了近旁的一个小土坑；那是他昨晚掘的。归土，他想，归土，这是生命最后的选择了，也是一种天命罢。</p> <p>白须老者撑着腰走向河流，俯身扬起河水泼在脸上。远远地，沿着河岸走来一个身着白衫的少女，氤氲水汽中，她的垂肩黑发仿佛一小滩跌水披散下来，倔强的下巴和眼镜后的眼睛同时显出一种年轻的快乐和奔波的疲态。</p> <p>“嗨！”少女流露出惊讶的神色，“你好！不好意思请问一下，这是哪里？”</p> <p>“好问题，”白须老者微笑着眯起眼，“其实吧，我也说不上来。你要去哪里？或许我可以指路。”</p> <p>“唔，我也不知道，”少女说着自己也笑了，“学什么呢？从事什么工作呢？或学习工程技术，将知识用于工业生产或技术服务；或学习生产供求关系，将知识用于辅助投资，最大化收益；或学习法律法规，为他人提供法律服务。总之是去往更美好的生活吧。”</p> <p>白须老者皱起了眉，“这些听起来都不是追求幸福的正道啊。工程技术，不过人造机事；所谓生产供求，最大化收益，又存机心于胸；而所谓律法，是人设立的法律制度，去研究其中的原委与理性，甚至辩驳、找寻有利于己方的观点与证据，岂不是落入辩士之流？大言炎炎，小言詹詹，词费之论，恐怕难逃小言吧？”</p> <p>少女嗔怒似的抱起双臂，然后看笑话似的又放下：“照你说来，仿佛‘自然、本真’，那是人生‘正确’的追求，但你看这些野草啊，”她弯下腰，指着繁荣滋长的草木，“它们也许永远也许没有探求本真的心态，但它们也是自然的一部分；它们不过就是想汲取阳光、滋养生命，又有什么值得批评的呢？我想从事的工作，不过就是一种生活方式罢了，又为什么横加指责呢？”</p> <p>早晨的阳光开始展现光彩。映着薄雾，野草上的露珠闪烁着晶莹的光辉，折射出明丽的霓虹，仿佛在宣告新一天到来的讯息，又仿佛宣言着逐渐苏醒的新的远航。老者痴迷地坐倒在地，不顾少女好奇的目光，口中念念有词，仿佛梦中呓语：</p> <p>“大道不称，大辩不言，大仁不仁，大廉不嗛，大勇不忮。非彼无我，非我无所取。天地与我并生，而万物与我为一。”说到这里，白须老者弥散的双目焕发出灿烂的光彩，迷惘的嘴角突然洋溢着笑意。他回过神来，抬起头，定睛瞧着少女：“就是这样，对吗？我是真君的一个具体实现，你也是；我是自然规律的体现，你也是；无功是我的追求，有功是你的造化；无机是我的喜好，有机是人类社会的统一表现……”</p> <p>“嗯……”少女调皮地调了下眼，半信半疑，“对吧。”</p> <p>白须老者认真地看着少女，而后毫无征兆地大笑起来。“我也没什么东西给你做纪念品，”他笑呵呵地说，“要不，我给你摘些野草，做个花环？”</p> <p>“你说好给我指路的！”</p> <p>“当然，当然。我听人们说起过，你要的那种生活就在河的对岸。你也许可以用这个空葫芦渡河。”老者扬起手边的大葫芦，“事实上——”他站了起来，“我也要过去了。”</p> <p>“你不呆在这里吗？”少女困惑地问，“隐居起来，冠一个洁身自好之名？”</p> <p>“本来是这样的，”白须老者道，“但是，你瞧：大方无隅，大器晚成，大音希声，大象无形，大隐无名。这是前人说的。庸也者，用也；用也者，通也；通也者，得也。这是我说的。所以，”他跨出一大步，“你到底还要不要花环了？”</p> <p>“不用了，”少女扑哧一声笑了出来。</p> <p>“你要知道没必要为了保护几株野草而——”</p> <p>“我知道，”少女回头望了一眼草地，轻声打断了老者，“但我现在就是这样想的。草在结它的种子，风在摇它的叶子。我们不做什么，就很美好。”</p> <p>阳光和野草的注视中，老者和少女坐在大葫芦上，荡过河去。一阵风吹来，拂过野草的叶片，拂过少女的发间，然后，又吹向对岸熙熙攘攘的人群。</p> <p>（完）</p> <p><br/></p> <p><strong>说明：</strong></p> <p>此文初作于2016年5月底，第三部分原较为具体，与专业选择有关。修订于2024年2月，第三部分有较大改动。</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Life"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[草在结它的种子，风在摇它的叶子。我们站着，不说话，就十分美好。 ——顾城《门前》]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gallery of plots generated by nonlinear dynamics</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/beautiful_plots_dynamics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gallery of plots generated by nonlinear dynamics"/><published>2023-10-01T16:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-10-01T16:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/beautiful_plots_dynamics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/beautiful_plots_dynamics/"><![CDATA[<p>Nonlinear dynamical systems are known to generate interesting patterns as their trajectories in phase space. This gallery includes some of these pretty patterns, most of which come from my nonlinear dynamics class.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/pendulum_trajectories-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/pendulum_trajectories-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/pendulum_trajectories-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/pendulum_trajectories.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Trajectories of the nonlinear pendulum in the phase space. The orderly yet rich pattern resembles that of a Persian carpet. </div> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/pendulum_FTLE-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/pendulum_FTLE-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/pendulum_FTLE-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/pendulum_FTLE.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Finite time Lyapunov exponent (FTLE) of the nonlinear pendulum in the phase space. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Sci-Tech"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nonlinear dynamical systems are known to generate interesting patterns as their trajectories in phase space.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">List of word plays to be used as titles</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/title_puns/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="List of word plays to be used as titles"/><published>2023-07-05T02:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-05T02:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/title_puns</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/title_puns/"><![CDATA[<p>This is a continuously updated list of paronomasia or interesting acronyms, or word plays in general, that can be used as titles of papers, books, punchlines in presentations, names of products, etc.</p> <p>In rare circumstances where these items are actually used, please give me (and coauthors) some credit ;)</p> <ul> <li><strong><em>Fast and Fourier’s</em></strong> <ul> <li>Origin: A hybrid between the movie franchise <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fast_%26_Furious"><em>Fast and Furious</em></a> and the algorithm Fast Fourier Transform (FFT).</li> <li>Possible scenario: For papers, new techniques, libraries or algorithms on Fourier transforms; alternatively, may also be used for denoting efficient thermal instruments (using another field where Fourier has important contributions).</li> <li>Author: J Min, V Giraud, D Tolmachev</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong><em>Music of the Rotating Sphere</em></strong> <ul> <li>Origin: Modified from <a href="https://www.discogs.com/artist/29735-Coldplay">Coldplay</a>’s album <a href="https://www.discogs.com/release/20587606-Coldplay-Music-Of-The-Spheres"><em>Music of the Spheres</em></a></li> <li>Possible scenario: For research works on fluid dynamics in a rotating sphere, especially those concerned with eigenmodes and/or resonances.</li> <li>Author: J Min</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong><em>AquaM-EN/AquaMEN</em></strong>: <strong>Aqua</strong>tic <strong>M</strong>odel of <strong>E</strong>arthquake <strong>N</strong>ucleation <ul> <li>Origin: Modified from DC Comic’s <a href="https://www.dc.com/characters/aquaman">Aquaman</a>.</li> <li>Possible scenario: For research works on simulation of earthquake nucleation associated with fluid/water effects. Ideally, the works should involve earthquake nucleation in marine or water environment, but this scenario seems highly unlikely. Therefore, multi-phase flows that involve fluid phases should also count.</li> <li>Author: J Min</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong><em>Poly Cow</em></strong> <ul> <li>Origin: Modified from the Swiss burger restaurant <a href="https://www.holycow.ch/en/">Holy Cow</a>. Amazingly, I always thought this was just a one-store restaurant on Zähringerstrasse, but it turned out to be a chain.</li> <li>Possible scenario: establishing a burger place in or very close to ETH zentrum campus, e.g. on the same floor with bQm, Einstein Zweistein. May however be sued by Holy Cow.</li> <li>Author: J Min</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p><br/></p> <hr/> <h3 id="the-poly-franchise">The Poly Franchise</h3> <ul> <li>Origin: from the pre-existing names of ETH facilities/events containing “poly” (e.g. <em>Polyterrasse</em>, <em>Polybahn</em>, <em>Polymesse</em>, <em>Polyball</em>, etc.). Meant to be used in a similar way as the prefix “Mc”.</li> <li><strong><em>PolySchnitzel</em></strong>: Schnitzel, preferably on a stick. Can also be used to name a Schnitzel truck that offers Schnitzels on sticks.</li> <li><strong><em>PolyNuggests</em></strong>: Nuggets.</li> <li><strong><em>PolyChicken</em></strong>: Chicken.</li> <li><strong><em>PolyFish</em></strong>: Fish.</li> <li><strong><em>Big Poly</em></strong>: Supposed to be a big hamburger, but we already have <em>Poly Cow</em> for the burger series?</li> <li>Author: EPM group</li> </ul> <p><br/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Sci-Tech"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[of articles or books, punchlines in presentations, names of products (continuously updated)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Absurdity and familiarity in sitcoms</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/sitcom_scale/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Absurdity and familiarity in sitcoms"/><published>2023-06-17T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-17T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/sitcom_scale</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/sitcom_scale/"><![CDATA[<p>I have watched my fair share of sitcoms - I mean for a person my age. For a person born in the eighties or earlier, I suppose it would be a lot easier to watch large amounts of sitcoms, as sitcoms used to be something that were aired on TV fairly regularly, thus well integrated into everyday life. Not anymore, no. These days people are no longer waiting in front of their TVs for their favourite show to start (do people still even talk about their favourite “TV shows”?). Even for people that still watch quite a lot TV series/movies, sitcoms is no longer a popular go-to genre these days.</p> <p>How sitcoms gradually lost their popuarlity and faded into the “out-dated” background is a discussion for another day. One does notice, however, that throughout the years, some successful sitcoms have seen calls for reunion, sequels or rebranding; and some of these proposals have actually been realized. To name a few, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt11337862/"><em>Friends: The Reunion</em> (2021)</a>, a reunion special of perhaps the most successful sitcom of all time, was produced 17 years after the last episode had been aired, not to mention the <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0375355/"><em>Joey</em> (2004-2006)</a> show that followed directly. The prequel to <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0898266/"><em>The Big Bang Theory</em> (2007-2019)</a>, <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt6226232/"><em>Young Sheldon</em> (2017-)</a> started even before the original show ended. And just last year, the streaming platform Hulu launched <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt14500082/"><em>How I Met Your Father</em> (2022-)</a>, a rebranding of the show <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0460649/"><em>How I Met Your Mother</em> (2005-2014)</a> which ended eight years ago.</p> <p>Granted, not all these attempts for resurrecting the old sitcoms are successful. <em>How I Met Your Father</em>, for instance, seems to have already gained an ill name, one year after its launch. Nevertheless, these attempts at least show that there is certain nostalgia in the viewership of certain sitcoms that can be leveraged, or further exploited. In constrast, some equally (if not more) critically-acclaimed and popular sitcoms never seem to have received similar attention. For instance, no one seems to be willing to bring <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0118689/">Bean (1997)</a> back on the TV screen. There are several movies under the <em>Johnny English</em> franchise, which share quite some similarities with <em>Bean</em>, but do not count towards this. Nor does it seem in anyone’s need to bring back <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0487831/"><em>The IT Crowd</em> (2006-2013)</a>.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/himym_characters-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/himym_characters-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/himym_characters-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/himym_characters.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Five main characters from <i>How I Met Your Mother</i>. </div> <p>What caused the difference? One might argue that it is more challenging to produce sequels to <em>Bean</em> or <em>The IT crowd</em>. This argument is reasonable in that Rowan Atkinson is an irreplaceable actor, and he is now slightly old to shoot a new series like that. However, the humor in <em>Bean</em> and <em>The IT crowd</em> is actually more time-invariant. In fact, resurrecting Mr. Bean might be more feasible in the sense that the show simply intended to potrait a silly and clumsy man, and so these jokes do not really go out of date or require modern modification. On the other hand, jokes in <em>How I Met Your Mother</em> may already been seen as stereotypical or sexually offensive, or “offensive” in general in the modern context (given that the series only ended less than 10 years ago, it is remarkable how rapidly people’s perception of offensiveness changed in the past decade). <strong>Therefore, the willingness of the audience to see a spin-off of <em>Friends</em> instead of <em>Beans</em> seems to indicate difference in style between these shows that attracts their respective audience, which I attribute to their relative amount of absurdity and familiarity.</strong></p> <p>Absurdity is an essential ingredient in virtually all successful sitcoms. Indeed, all sitcoms must resort to violation of familiar responses and behaviours in order to create humor. The extent of such absurdity, however, may vary on a broad spectrum, which I call the absurdity-familiarity spectrum. Sitcoms that cluster near the familiar endmember creates ticklish jokes from slight or mild violation of everyday scenes. Sitcoms clustering near the absurd endmember, on the other hand, more significantly alienate the characters from the regular life the audience are familiar with.</p> <p>Let us take a step back, and look at the big picture of all these sitcoms. On one side, you have a warmhouse flower who, after running away from the wedding, joined her five friends, and over the years learned to gained independence, while witnessing three marriages between them (<em>Friends</em>); a romantic guy on his nine-year-long pursuit of love and happiness, accompanied by his friends (<em>How I Met Your Mother</em>); and a bunch of nerds who, after an attractive waitress entered their lives, slowly became less and less socially awkward, and somehow ended up in happy marriages (and with a Nobel price) (<em>The Big Bang Theory</em>). On the other side, you have a clumsy man doing awkward things every day (<em>Bean</em>), and a woman joining the IT department and having strange adventures with her colleagues (<em>The IT Crowd</em>).</p> <p>Do you see the difference? While in the former category, the characters are like realistic human beings, living their lives and growing, with all kinds of time scales all present, the characters in the latter category seems to living the same day over and over again. No, I am not talking about Groundhog day; people still do different things every day. Today, Mr. Bean goes swimming, and Jen serves as an italian interpreter. The next day, Mr. Bean goes to take an exam, and Moss enters a spelling competition. Different things still happen, and every day is a different story. But on a larger time scale, nothing ever happens. Nobody gets born, nobody falls in love, nothing changes in people’s relationships (apart from a thrilling one-night stand for Jen and Roy, which also sees no consequence whatsoever in later episodes), nobody gets married, and nobody dies (nobody relevant to the story anyway). Characters in these sitcoms live a surreal life where nothing develops on a long time scale, and experience the same routine day-in, day-out.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Culture"/><category term="sitcoms"/><category term="Friends"/><category term="HIMYM"/><category term="TBBT"/><category term="Bean"/><category term="TheITCrowd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing the absurdity-familiarity scale]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project ZHzh - a Chinese translation of Zürich public transportation map</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/zvv_map_translation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project ZHzh - a Chinese translation of Zürich public transportation map"/><published>2023-04-23T02:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-23T02:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/zvv_map_translation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/zvv_map_translation/"><![CDATA[<p>It all started out as a simple question out of curiosity: what do these road names and tram stop names that I pass by every day in the trams mean? I have been asking myself this since my first year in Zürich, when I still took Tram 6 along the Limmat to school every day. Sure, some of the names are evident - “Löwenbräu” for “Lion Brewery”, “Bernoulli-Häuser” for “Bernoulli houses”, “Fischerweg” for “Fisherman path” - these are really just German words that can be easily translated. Others are more tricky. For instance, what is “quai” in “Bahnhofquai”? Where is the “turm” in “Hardturm”? <em>[There is indeed a tower connected to a large parking lot at Hardturm, but I am almost certain that does not amount to the Turm]</em> And are the Bernoulli-Häuser actually associated with the Basel Bernoulli family?</p> <p>Thus began my side project of translating the map of city Zürich into Chinese. At first sight, it seems an easy-peasy work to do, but the mere number of tram stops, train stations and bus stops to be translated already signals a time-consuming task. It also doesn’t help that the etymology of these names are from several different sources. The <a href="https://www.stadt-zuerich.ch/prd/de/index/stadtarchiv/strassennamen.html">Strassennamen-Datenbank der Stadt Zürich</a> comprises perhaps the most comprehensive soure of street name origins, but falls short for non-street names and names with complicated history. In these circumstances, <a href="https://www.alt-zueri.ch/turicum/index.htm">alt-zueri.ch</a> is usually a good reference, in particular for special land names. In some cases, Wikipedia can also prove useful, for land names that originate in old German or other old tongue, well before the Medieval times. And in very rare cases, I find useful information only in some brochures on history compiled by local historians or librarians from the corresponding Quartiervereine.</p> <p>Although the work is still ongoing, please allow me to present the Chinese translation of the neighbourhoods of city Zürich, as well as the translation of the 110-zone map of ZVV:</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Karte_Gemeinde_Z%C3%BCrich_zh-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Karte_Gemeinde_Z%C3%BCrich_zh-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Karte_Gemeinde_Z%C3%BCrich_zh-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Karte_Gemeinde_Z%C3%BCrich_zh.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> German-Chinese correspondance of the Gemeinde names of City Zürich. </div> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/zvv-stadt-zuerich_zh-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/zvv-stadt-zuerich_zh-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/zvv-stadt-zuerich_zh-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/zvv-stadt-zuerich_zh.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Chinese translation of the 110-zone map of ZVV public transport, City Zürich. </div> <p> Download link for the full PDF version of ZVV 110-zone map: <a href="/assets/pdf/zvv-stadt-zuerich_zh.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"> <i class="fas fa-file-pdf"></i> </a> </p> <p>As it turns out, not surprisingly, the land names and street names have several different types of origins. Many of these named are actual words conjugated together, which may indicate the previous landscape. “Albisrieden” indicates a wetland of reeds at the rim of <em>Albis</em>; “Werdhözli” is a small forest on <em>Werd</em>, an island in the middle of the Limmat river. Many others, though look like actual words, are named after families that once lived nearby, or after well-known persons. For instance, “Eschergutweg” is named after the <em>Escher</em>s’ nearby; and there is no <em>Schaufel</em> or any kind of <em>Berg</em> near “Schaufelbergerstrasse”, but just a person named Arnold Schaufelberger. Some of them are named after companies, present or historical, that are or once were the nuclei of the neighbourhoods. These include the “Siemens” station in the southwest, apparently named after the company <em>Siemens</em>, and “Schweizer Rück”, named after the reinsurance company <em>SwissRe</em>.</p> <p>For the most translation work, I try to precise so that the original meaning of the language is preserved. But at some point, I have to stop. There is some vague explanation on Wikipedia, saying “Werd” itself may be an old word for river island; or “Letzi” may be an old Swiss word for defense works. These words have no correspondance in Chinese (or English) that is both accurate and “local” enough. And the same thing happens in Chinese - and I bet, all other languages - although some words or characters carry their own meanings, the meanings are lost over the centries when these words are used in region names. There is etymology to almost every name of village and town, but quite often people no longer recall their original meanings in the modern context. Eventually, I have to stop somewhere, and do the <em>transliteration</em>.</p> <p>Of course, sometimes I play with the not-so-strict translation, simply to make the translated name <em>more Chinese</em>, more culturally close, and more interesting to read. Oerlikon has nothing to do with avacado, except for the fact that they pronounce similarly in Chinese; the same thing holds for Milchbuck, Fluntern, etc. For completeness, I intend to list the etymology details of the entries below. But please let me have the fun part also ;)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Travel"/><category term="Zürich"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Translation? or maybe just transliteration?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Wave equation solver generated by New Bing</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/newbing_wave_eqn/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wave equation solver generated by New Bing"/><published>2023-03-11T02:12:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-11T02:12:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/newbing_wave_eqn</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2023/newbing_wave_eqn/"><![CDATA[<p>Despite not being a real hipster when it comes to latest technology, when MS Edge asked if I wanted to be on the waitlist for their AI-powered new Bing, I gladly agreed. Due to the existing rumors and demos using ChatGPT, I was indeed quite excited when I got the chance two days later to access their new Bing, and I had high expectations as well.</p> <p>I tried to test its ability of combining code generation and physics/maths comprehension, so <strong>I asked it to generate a solver code in Python for wave equation.</strong> New Bing returned the following python code.</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># Import numpy and matplotlib libraries
</span><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">numpy</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">np</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">matplotlib.pyplot</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">plt</span>

<span class="c1"># Define the parameters of the wave equation
</span><span class="n">c</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span> <span class="c1"># Wave speed
</span><span class="n">L</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">10</span> <span class="c1"># Domain length
</span><span class="n">T</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">10</span> <span class="c1"># Final time
</span><span class="n">nx</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">101</span> <span class="c1"># Number of grid points in space
</span><span class="n">nt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">101</span> <span class="c1"># Number of grid points in time
</span><span class="n">dx</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">L</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">nx</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1"># Spatial step size
</span><span class="n">dt</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">T</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">nt</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="c1"># Temporal step size
</span>
<span class="c1"># Check the stability condition
</span><span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">c</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dt</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">dx</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">:</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">The scheme is unstable. Please choose smaller dt or larger dx.</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
    <span class="nf">exit</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="c1"># Define the initial condition function
</span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">u0</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">exp</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">10</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">L</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Define the boundary condition function
</span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">g</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">t</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span>

<span class="c1"># Create the grid points in space and time
</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">linspace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">L</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">t</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">linspace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">T</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Initialize the solution array with zeros
</span><span class="n">u</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">zeros</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="n">nt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nx</span><span class="p">))</span>

<span class="c1"># Apply the initial condition at t=0
</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,:]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">u0</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Apply the boundary condition at x=0 and x=L for all t
</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[:,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">g</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">t</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[:,</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">g</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">t</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Loop over the interior points and apply the finite difference scheme
</span><span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span> <span class="c1"># Time loop
</span>    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nx</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span> <span class="c1"># Space loop
</span>        <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">c</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dt</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">])</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">c</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">])</span>

<span class="c1"># Plot the solution at different times using matplotlib animation 
</span><span class="kn">from</span> <span class="n">matplotlib.animation</span> <span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">FuncAnimation</span>

<span class="n">fig</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">ax</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">subplots</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">line</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">ax</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">plot</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,:])</span>
<span class="n">ax</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlim</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">L</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylim</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mf">1.5</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mf">1.5</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_xlabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">x</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ylabel</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">u</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">ax</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_title</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Wave equation solution</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">animate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="n">line</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set_ydata</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,:])</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">line</span>

<span class="n">anim</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nc">FuncAnimation</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">fig</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">animate</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">frames</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="n">nt</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">interval</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">100</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">plt</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">show</span><span class="p">()</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>This is an elegant piece of code, it has reasonable comments, good variable namings, and the entire structure is very much like a numerical modelling code. It also includes a nice animation snippet for visualization. It even safeguards the model with a condition on the CFL number.</p> <p>The code is ready to run, and produces an animation as follows.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-2"> </div> <div class="col-sm-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/animation.gif-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/animation.gif-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/animation.gif-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/animation.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-2"> </div> </div> <p>At first sight, it seems to be perfectly reasonable, even better than reasonable - there is no significant numerical diffusion, something unavoidable for finite difference schemes. But then, under closer inspection, two unexpected things emerge:</p> <ul> <li>As the wave packet reaches the boundary, there is no reflection.</li> <li>There is no left-travelling wave, only the right-travelling one.</li> </ul> <p>For the first problem, I thought New Bing might have used an absorbing boundary, e.g. Gaussian tapering, PML, etc. As I checked the code, however, it was obvious that it only used homogeneous Dirichlet boundary condition. For the second issue, a possible explanation is that the code uses specific velocity initial conditions. However, the initial condition is also quite straightforward - only one initial condition on displacement.</p> <p>My confusion spiralled after checking the code for five minutes, when I realized <strong><em>I didn’t even recognize the form of this “wave equation” time stepping scheme!</em></strong> This time stepper uses only the displacement field from the previous time step, hence only approximates a first-order time derivative in the equation:</p> <div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># Loop over the interior points and apply the finite difference scheme
</span><span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">n</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nt</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span> <span class="c1"># Time loop
</span>    <span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">i</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="nf">range</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">nx</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">):</span> <span class="c1"># Space loop
</span>        <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">c</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dt</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">])</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">c</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dt</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">dx</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="mi">2</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="n">u</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="n">n</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">i</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">])</span>
</code></pre></div></div> <p>Writing down the formula on the white board, I came to the conclusion that this is simply not a wave equation. It seems to be some kind of advection-diffusion equation, which advects the packet to the right at velocity \(c\), and one with incorrect dimensions at that. It still seems a bit peculiar that the code is stable. Normally when a central difference is used that involves downstream/downwind grids, instability develops in the system. I attribute the stability to the diffusion term.</p> <p>As a final attempt, <strong>I asked New Bing to explain the finite difference scheme used in the code</strong>. Its answer is as follows (maths contents prettified).</p> <hr/> <p>Sure. The finite difference scheme is a method to approximate the solution of a partial differential equation (PDE) such as the wave equation by discretizing the space and time domains into a grid of points and replacing the derivatives in the PDE by finite differences. For example, the wave equation in one dimension is:</p> \[u_{tt} = c^2 u_{xx}\] <p>where u(x,t) is the displacement of the wave at position x and time t, and c is the wave speed. To apply the finite difference scheme, we introduce a uniform grid with spacing dx in space and dt in time:</p> \[x_i = i\, dx \quad \mathrm{for}\, i = 0, 1, \cdots, n_x - 1,\quad t_n = ndt \quad \mathrm{for}\, n = 0, 1, \cdots, n_t-1\] <p>Then we denote \(u_i^n\) as an approximation of \(u(x_i,t_n)\) at the grid point \((x_i,t_n)\). The goal is to find \(u_i^n\) for all i and n using a recursive formula. To do that, we need to approximate the second derivatives in the wave equation by finite differences. One possible way to do that is to use central differences:</p> \[u_{tt} (x_i, t_n) \approx (u_i^{n+1} - 2 u_i^n + u_i^{n-1}) / dt^2, \qquad u_{xx} (x_i,t_n) \approx (u_{i+1}^n - 2 u_i^n + u_{i-1}^n) / dx^2\] <p>Substituting these approximations into the wave equation and rearranging terms gives:</p> \[u_i^{n+1} = u_i^n - \frac{cdt}{2dx} (u_{i+1}^n - u_{i-1}^n) + \frac{c^2 dt^2}{2dx^2}(u_{i+1}^n - 2 u_i^n + u_{i-1}^n)\] <p>This formula allows us to compute \(u_i^{n+1}\) from the values of u at time level n and n-1. However, we also need some initial and boundary conditions to start and complete the computation. The initial condition specifies the initial shape of the wave at t=0:</p> \[u(x,0) = f(x)\] <p>The boundary condition specifies how the wave behaves at the ends of the domain x=0 and x=L:</p> \[u(0,t) = g(t),\quad u(L,t) = h(t)\] <p>To apply these conditions on the grid, we need to evaluate them at \(x_0=0\) and \(x_{n_x-1}=L\) for all t_n:</p> \[u_0^n = g(t_n),\quad u_{n_x-1}^n = h(t_n)\] <p>and at all x_i for t_0=0:</p> \[u_i^0 = f(x_i)\] <p>These values are known from given functions f,g,h or data. Once we have them, we can use them along with the formula above to compute all other values of u on the grid.</p> <hr/> <p>Now it is quite clear that although the GPT model has knowledge on the correct formulation of FDM, it failed to perform the task of correctly combining the terms together. This again seems to be part of the flaw of symbolic derivation and computation. The code certainly is elegant, and might well pass for a real “wave equation” solver at first sight, just without the correct physics.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Sci-Tech"/><category term="GPT"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I tried to let new Bing generate a wave equation simulator. The result - nice visualization code, seemingly correct structure, wrong physics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Central Europe 2022 - Bratislava - Prague</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2022/Bratislava_Prague/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Central Europe 2022 - Bratislava - Prague"/><published>2022-11-02T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-02T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2022/Bratislava_Prague</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2022/Bratislava_Prague/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="bratislava">Bratislava</h2> <p><br/></p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_castle-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_castle-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_castle-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_castle.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The Bratislava castle. </div> <p>On the 29th of October I left Budapest for the Slovakian capital, Bratislava. The first segment of my ride, numbered EuroCity 142, also named “Liszt Ferenc”, ran from Budapest to Wien. It was named after the Hungarian composer Liszt Ferenc (Franz Liszt), whose piano was among the most precious collections of the national museum of Hungary (it was said to be previously used by Beethoven, and was kept in a special room with carefully adjusted temperature and humidity). The train ride was not long, but I transferred at the tiny border town of Hegyeshalom. It was a very small town, with no business whatsoever near the train station. Judging from the map at the station, there was one main street for the town, where you could find some shops like pharmacy, restaurant, etc. The waiting area was in the same room with the ticket office, and consisted of just two benches. It reminded me of some small county train stations in China, but probably back to twenty years ago. My second ride from Hegyeshalom to Bratislava featured a very small train carriage, one that was even shorter than some trams in Zürich.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_train-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_train-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_train-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_train.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_station-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_station-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_station-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_station.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Left: the crowded train to Bratislava "Liszt Ferenc"; right: the tiny train station Hegyeshalom. </div> <p>The fog that had shadowed Budapest apparently followed Danube to Bratislava. The I-cannot-see-across-the-Danube situation continued and worsened. When on the second day I ascended to the top of the castle hill, trying to get a glimpse of the river view, the most prominent view I could see was the construction site right at the foot of the hill. The bridge, together with the cars and the buildings on the other side of the Danube, was covered in thick fog. As I wandered along the Danube, I saw warnings for low visibility displayed on an electronic screen. According to the displayed map, the warning was almost nation wide. As a result, my stay in Bratislava was shadowed by the foggy, humid coldness, not the ideal weather for a person who just recovered from fever and cold. I changed to warmer clothes during my stay, but still constantly felt cold outdoors.</p> <p>Fortunately, I had several delicious and heart-warming meals here. As I reached Bratislava, I could sense that the consumer price was no longer as low as that in Budapest or Ljubljana. However, with 10 euros one could still have a very decent meal. The first evening in Bratislava, I had a good bowl of chicken soup Ramen with a bottle of sparkling Rooibata (“Lemonade,” the lady at the restaurant explained, but this was quite different). The small Japanese restaurant was located on the main street near my hostel, and was also popular for its sushi, judging from the takeaway orders they were distributing. On the second day I had a hearty meal of burger and fries for lunch. The burger had thick juicy beef, a greasy slice of bacon, and was filled with the melted cheddar. The french fries came with a chili ketchup sauce, which added a different flavor. In the evening I tried to look for some local cuisine, and after seeing the people waiting for tables in Slovak Pub, I went to a local restaurant called Gladius. The restaurant had a quiet and private ambience, and the food was of reasonable price and good quality. I spent less than 6 euros on a creamy garlic soup and a beer. The beer was surprisingly light and fresh, and the soup, although slightly salty to my taste, was still very tasty.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_beer-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_beer-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_beer-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_beer.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_garlic_soup-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_garlic_soup-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_garlic_soup-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_garlic_soup.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A nice beer and a bowl of garli coup make a good meal. </div> <p>The entire central-eastern Europe has a quite strong Catholic ambience. Except for the grand cathedrals in Budapest and Prague, most churches were still mostly reserved for religious purposes rather than for tourism. In Ljubljana, for instance, I saw an aged couple went for confession one after another. As my first day in Bratislava was Sunday, I was able to witness several holy mass. In the morning I was at St. Stefan church, and the holy mass was accompanied by choir music. There was a homeless person outside the church door, singing along the music. Around noon I was at St. Martin’s cathedral, and there was again a holy mass (in fact, according to the schedule, there were multiple ones in the morning, at noon, and in the afternoon). There were more tourists as St. Martin’s cathedral was located near the old town, and I was able to enter briefly with other tourists a bit inside the entrance to get a glimpse. People were following one another in a queue in front of the altar. After the ritual, they went back to their seats to pray. Some people, including some young people, actually kneeled on the ground when praying.</p> <p>The old town of Bratislava, the major attraction within the city, is of the similar size as Ljubljana. Both old towns are also accompanied by a castle, located on an adjacent hill. As both places had Slavic languages as their first language, the two cities had similar vibes, although Ljubljana seemed to be cleaner and tidier. Tired of visiting museums, I only walked through the old town, and looked at the outside of the castle, the national museum and the national gallery. The gate to the old town, Michael’s gate, was under restoration, and was again covered by scaffolds. There was also a large area of construction site at the foot of the castle hill, and significantly deteriorates the view of the watchpoint outside the castle. Meanwhile, I spent slightly more time indoors, and had a chat with my Welsh roommate Gavin, whose name was derived from the knight of the round table, Gawain. Having lived in Liverpool for many years, he was very fond of the city and highly recommended me to visit. Manchester is also good, but Liverpool is better, he said. No, not because of the football team, just the city.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-9"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_path_to_castle-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_path_to_castle-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_path_to_castle-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_path_to_castle.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-3"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_la_komika-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_la_komika-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_la_komika-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/bratislava_la_komika.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Left: the narrow lane through the town leading to the castle hill; right: what appears to be a theater, La Komika. </div> <p><br/></p> <hr/> <h2 id="prague">Prague</h2> <p><br/></p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_train_station-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_train_station-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_train_station-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_train_station.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Old hall of the Praha train station. </div> <p>I was awoken from my sleep by twinkling lights dancing before my eyelids. It was forty minutes since the train left Brno and headed northwest for Prague, and the thick mist that had haunted the central European mountains and plains, as well as my journey in Budapest and Bratislava for the past four days, was finally lifted. Now the sunlight shone unhampered through a clear atmosphere; and by clear I mean the clear blue sky that is so typical of a Beijing autumn day, extending to the farthest visible depth. It is in this clear weather that one gets to appreciate the true diversity of the magnificent sunlight. The olive green from the corniferous, the twinkling gold and flaming red from the trees, and the highlights that are reflected from prancing waves and swirling eddies of the running streams. All these colours that had been diminished in the darkenss of the mist now vividly came together, as if a world brought back to life.</p> <p>As I arrived at Praha main station and was walking in the underground tunnel, my eyes were caught by the sunlight shining down through a small opening. Looking up, I saw a magnificent train hall above the tunnel, lightened by sunlight shining through splendid windows, almost as in a Catholic church. The train station was then connected to a lovely central park, where people were walking their dogs, eating snacks or reading a book. One couldn’t see this beautiful scene on a golden autumn afternoon without feeling touched. Thus began my stay in my favorite city along my journey.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_square-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_square-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_square-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_square.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_karlova-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_karlova-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_karlova-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_karlova.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_charles-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_charles-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_charles-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_charles.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Left to right: Staromestska Namesti, Universita Karlova, Charles Bridge </div> <p>Prague first struck me as a city with numerous medieval, renaissance and baroque bearings. As one walks through the old town, the restored Medieval style gate towers, and the grand Staromestske Namesti (old town square), the Universita Karlova (Charles University), and the Charles bridge, all remind people of Prague’s once prominent role in the Luxembourg, as well as the later Habsburg Holy Roman Empire, and its status as the seat of the empire during Charles IV’s reign. The plaques of Universita Karlova on the wall, and the sculptures on the Charles bridge, although might not be the original, take visitors back to more than six centuries ago. The Vltava, which transverses most of Bohemia before coming to Prague, is cleaner, although smaller, than the Danube, and paints a more delicate ambience on the old town of Prague, as compared to Budapest and Bratislava. I stood on the bridge and looked northwards, imagining the Vltava merging into the Elbe in the far north, flowing past Berlin, my final destination, into the Baltic sea. A few days later I would stand on the bank of the Elbe, in front of a remnant segment of the Berlin Wall. It is indeed fascinating how the flowing water always arouses a strong sense of connection, something that not a road, not even a railway, can achieve.</p> <p>Across the Vltava from the old town lies another major attraction, and one of my favorite attractions, the Prague castle. Despite its name, the so-called Prague castle is different from the other castles I have visited. Those castles either served as a fort/Medieval style residence of a feudal lord (Heidelberg, Ljubljana, Bratislava), or as a renaissance-Baroque palace of the Holy Roman Empire noblemen (Buda). The Prague castle, however, is much richer than that. There is the usual royal palace, which has been the residence of the Bohemian throne from Medieval to modern ages, and was home to at least two emperors, Charles IV and Rudolph II, and which, over the years, acquired a hybrid Gothic-Renaissance style. The office chamber of the palace witnessed the famous 1618 defenestration. As the Catholic lords and their secretary were thrown out of the tower window by the Protestant lords, a long-time unrest, later known as the Thirty Years’ War, which influenced the entire continental Europe, came into form. The palace is accompanied by two churches. St George’s Basilica, a Romanesque church, features a red facade and simple towers. St. Vitus Cathedral, on the other hand, is a Gothic style church, that is magnificent not only in its grand magnitude, but also in its stained glass decorations. For a person that was on his first trip to central and eastern Europe, these stained glasses were the most beautiful ones I had ever witnessed. In addition to these architectures, the Prague castle also comes with a narrow lane between the defensive wall and the palace-cathedral assembly, known as the Golden Lane. While the palace and the churches were indeed magnificent and served to awe, the Golden Lane was much more interesting and fun. Through this narrow lane, one could see the ordinary life of the miscellaneous people attached to the castle during the feudal ages. Guards, soldiers, goldsmiths, servants; their lives were vividly presented through the reconstruction of the living spaces, arsenal, defensive walls and narrow corridors in the towers, as well as the pub/restaurant where these people used to blow off steam. The golden lane was also close to two towers, which used to serve as prisons. The vivid reconstruction of the torture rooms and punishments, although frightening and uneasy to look at, provided an interesting perspective of the feudal ages. Surprisingly, the Golden lane maintained part of its functions and was home to a number of residents up until the dawn of WWI; here one could see the transition from the feudal age to the modern age, or the emergence of a modern nationalism republic from the old empire.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-8"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral_glass-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral_glass-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral_glass-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_cathedral_glass.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> St. Vitus Cathedral and the stained glass by Mucha. </div> <p>Prague continued to be a major cultural city in the early modern times, and the city seemed to be not sparing efforts in demonstrating this. You might bump into a modernist sculpture of Kafka (or in my case, a post-modernist giant rotating head of Kafka) around the corner, reminding you that although having composed his works in German, Franz Kafka was by nature a Bohemian writer. In the busy old town area you would find a museum of Alphonse Mucha, a popular illustrator artist of Art Nouveau, whose work on stained glasses was quietly sitting in St. Vitus Cathedral, reminding you that although having made his name in Paris, Mucha was a very nationalist person at heart. Perhaps more so were his twenty epic cycle paintings, named the Slavic Epic, but unfortunately these paintings were on exhibition in Moravia, and couldn’t be viewed in Prague. Finally, if one would go a bit further south in Praha 2, one would see the museum of Antonin Dvorak. The museum, originally Dvorak’s house, was a very small building. On the ground floor one got a glimpse of his lifetime and experiences, and on the first floor one got to dive deeper into his achievements. Given its size the curating was quite extraordinary. Not only are you able to look at the collections, including many of his private belongings, but also watch an excellent documentary outlining his life as a Bohemian national musician, and listen to all his compositions. Drawing inspirations from Bohemian and Moravian folk music, he gained international recognition and fame, and was also invited to the Unite States to help compose new music for the new founded land. Prior to my visit there, my deepest impression of him was his grand symphony “From the New World”; but after my visit, I was also deeply impressed by the fierce and passionate “Slavonic Dance”, and the pure lyric melody “Humoresque”. His music is never overly serious, dull or boring, but is always romantic as well as passionate. This most celebrated Czech musician and composer was, from every aspect, a representative of Czechian nationalist music, as I realized later that the first six notes of his popular Humoresque were used as the cue tone for broadcasting on Czech trains.</p> <p>As a keen explorer on foot, I also walked down streets and lanes of Praha 2, 3, 8 and 10, during which I acquired the impression that Prague was not only touristic, but also an amazing city to work and live. Apart from all the rich history and culture that attracts (for some, too many) tourists, Prague is also home to numerous interesting little shops, second-hand shops, restaurants, bistros, osterias, tapas bar / izakayas and pubs. On many streets one might see the boards showing Pilsner Urquell, a lager beer that the Czechs were most proud of. Unfortunately, having tried out beers in Ljubljana and Bratislava, I was no longer in the mood for these drinks, and had to reserve this famous Lager until my next visit. It came as a surprise that Prague had a significant Asian community, most notably the Vietnamese community. There were many so-called mini markets, which were virtually convenience stores, often just hundreds of meters or less from one another. These stores were frequently, almost always, run by east Asian descendents. Apart from that, modern or traditional Vietnamese restaurants could be seen all over the town area, the densest I had ever seen during my trip in central Europe. I had a hearty bowl of Pho Bo in one restaurant to the south of the center, and it tasted quite authentic, at least quite close to the rice noodle with soup in Guangxi. The friendly owner also offered a separate dish of sliced peperoni, which could be added to the Pho, and it was quite spicy.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_hill-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_hill-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_hill-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_hill.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_goulash-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_goulash-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_goulash-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_goulash.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_pho_bo-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_pho_bo-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_pho_bo-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_pho_bo.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The habitable Praha. Left to right: stairs by a hill near Faculty of Mathematics, Universita Karlova; goulash with garlic bread; a hearty bowl of Pho Bo. </div> <p>The habitability of Prague certainly attracted plenty of businesses and workers to settle here. An example of such was my encounter of Giuseppe, another highlight of my journey, whom I met in the hostel lounge. The first evening we met, he was using his laptop in the lounge, while I was reading a novel in the sofa. We stroke up a conversation, and it turned out, we were both following a UCL game that night, i.e. Liverpool against Napoli. Being an Italian, he naturally rooted for Napoli, which was not only 15 games unbeaten in the Italian League, but also humiliated Liverpool with a 4-1 win a month back. I, on the other hand, rooted for the troubled Liverpool, who was hanging around the 10th place in the Premiere League. Although we were unable to find a live streaming anywhere, our small conversation led to long talks spanning two evenings. Giuseppe was from Milano; he used to work in banking, and after some unsuccessful and prolonged interviews with UBS last year, he took up a position in ExxonMobil and switched to the energy industry. He was just coming to Prague for his new post, and had been looking for an apartment for several days. He was excited after finding out about my expertise as a geophysicist, and we talked about the rising electricity prices, energy crisis, and different means of renewable energies as replacements. He asked about the induced seismicity during hydraulic fracturing in shale gas exploration, and I told him that the supposedly clean high-enthalpy geothermal energy may induce similar seismicity. Later we talked about each other’s itineraries, and he strongly recommended the Way of St. James as an intense hiking trail. Time flew, and when we ended our chat, it was already over midnight. “You wouldn’t expect such a conversation at a hostel,” said he, tired but satisfied after the long talk, “but again, that is why we came to the hostel, right?”</p> <p>In addition to Giuseppe, I had another two interesting encounters at the hostel. The first evening I met an elderly man from Germany, who was almost asleep when I got back to my hostel. He was from near Leipzig, and upon hearing that I spoke a bit German, however, he got excited and told me about his great vacation in Turkey. For almost an hour he was shooting a train of German at me, and as a mere A-level learner, I struggled to keep up with his words and strived to understand the main idea by catching discrete words or sentences from his speech. You can go from Germany to Sofia, and then to Istanbul, and than to the Turkish beach, he said. For about twenty minutes, he complained how services, foods, and taxis were expensive in Germany, but so cheap and approachable in Turkey. “The hotel was really nice at the beach; breakfast, lunch, dinner, all included. At noon they have beef, Schnitzels, everything. Guess how much that cost?” He waved his hands at me, his eyes opened wide, waiting for his dramatic reveal. “Just 30 euros a day!” He went on to show me his leather jacket and straw hat that he bought as bargains in Turkey, both of which much cheaper than what you would expect in Germany. He was truly happy as a young boy. Where was I from, he asked. I was from China, but since two years I lived in Switzerland. Ah so, he exclaimed, die Schweiz! He really liked to use “ah so”. Der Strom auch teuer in der Schweiz? Nein, nein, I answered, ein bisschen teurer, aber das ist noch ok. He shook his head, das ist sehr teuer in Deutschland! He gestured a really high price with his hands separated wide apart. For some reason he reminded me of one dormitory manager in my high school. They both had white hair, were both short and lively, as well as friendly.</p> <p>On the same evening I met Hana, a girl from Moravia coming to Prague to enjoy her Halloween in the city. She dressed up as a really cool ghost bride, after using a lot of makeups. The next morning I was able to talk to her more over the hostel breakfast. “I have twenty-six different food allergies,” she said, sadly but proudly, “so I also have to be careful when choosing the makeups.” She had to take care of her grandparents while her mother was working, and that day was her day off. On hearing this, I thought she might be quite young, but it turned out she was already in her thirties. She went to Universita Karlova at my age, and worked on apple farms in UK for a while. She wanted to proceed to her masters, but as her grandparents were unable to take care of themselves, she had to go home and take up the job. She struck me as a very passionate and lively person, who was young at heart, which explained why I mistook her for a much younger age. She gave me a strong recommendation on the Sci-Fi series <em>The Expanse</em>. I decided to list <em>The Expanse</em> together with <em>Game of Thrones</em>, as the TV series that I should start watching when I had the chance.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_castle_night-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_castle_night-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_castle_night-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/praha_castle_night.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Praha castle at twilight. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Travel"/><category term="Slovakia"/><category term="Bratislava"/><category term="Czechia"/><category term="Prague"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Entering the land of the west Slavs.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Central Europe 2022 - Budapest</title><link href="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2022/Budapest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Central Europe 2022 - Budapest"/><published>2022-10-29T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-29T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2022/Budapest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gentlemin.github.io/blog/2022/Budapest/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="budapest">Budapest</h2> <p><br/></p> <p>At half past nine on the third day in Ljubljana I boarded the direct train to Budapest. The train, InterCity 247, was named “Citadella”, after the name of the citadel in Budapest. Ironically, I later found that the Citadella was completely closed to the public due to restoration (and the restoration was not a delicate one devoted to preservation, judging from the construction site). This was the longest train ride (excluding NightJet) on my journey, and in the end took almost eight hours including delay. The first half, i.e., the half within Slovenia was enjoyable. The carriage was not crowded, and I got to enjoy the views of the tranquil river valleys under the sun. I was excited, as Budapest had been listed one of the favourite cities by Lu and JMY, and I had great expectations for it. My excitement was however weakened as I entered Hungary. At that point the weather was turning to cloudy or overcast, and my back began to hurt because of the long travel. What made the situation worse was that the Hungary section of the journey was apparently subject to seat reservation. As more passengers with seat reservation boarded the train and mingled with those who didn’t, I had to change seat. When we finally arrived in Budapest, the crowded carriage reeked of exhaustion.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_citadella-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_citadella-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_citadella-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_citadella.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_tram-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_tram-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_tram-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/buda_tram.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Left: the hill hosting Citadella at night; right: tramways in Buda, along Danube. </div> <p>My stay in Budapest was shadowed by both bad weather and sickness. There was a mist accompanying the already melancholic overcast weather, which only grew thicker over the days. On my last day in Budapest one could barely see across the Danube. I ran a fever on the second day in Budapest, and felt dizzy for my entire stay. It was difficult to pinpoint where exactly I got infected, as there were too many people with common cold, flu or covid symptoms - significant symptoms. Not just sneezing, but constant coughing, and one of my roommates during my first night at the hostel talked weirdly in his sleep. “He has a fever,” Omar, who was also in the same room, and with whom I acquainted over the breakfast, said, “and I think he might be hallucinating in his sleep”. “This place (Hungary) was the first place to decide to completely leave covid behind,” Manuel, a Canadian with whom I had several long conversations, said satisfactorily, “I was able to come here last year when everywhere else was closed.” Given my health condition during my stay and all those people with significant symptoms but didn’t bother taking any precautions, I seriously doubt if that was a good piece of news. I, on the other hand, reinstated the mask obligation for myself in indoor areas after I showed symptoms, this time not to protect myself, but mostly for the protection of others.</p> <p>Despite the weather and sickness, I was still able to visit many places. Granted, some of my impressions were also negatively affected by my illness and the lighting, but I really couldn’t speak highly of the curation of the national museum, especially the exhibition on the first floor displaying historical artifacts since the 12th century. There were no rich illustrations, and the text explanations with small fonts were placed in all kinds of weird places - for instance, 50 centimeters above the ground - how was I even supposed to read this? Should I crouch down just to read the fine prints? The english versions of the text were often (let’s say, 80% of the boards) missing letters, because instead of printing the entire poster, they seemed to have printed/glued individual letters as a separate layer onto the boards. In most cases it was not hard to guess the missing letters, but the condition of the texts still slowed down reading. The prohibition of photography was also an unpleasant thing. The aged staff of the museums would patrol the exhibition, and prevent people from taking photos. Once I was only searching for additional info on Wikipedia on my smartphone when a staff member approached me and asked me to delete whatever photo I had taken. She also didn’t speak too much English, so we had to make do with our limited means of communication. I have seen prohibitions of photography in art galleries mostly, presumably due to copyright issues, but such prohibitions in a permanent historical artifact exhibition was quite unusual. Later I found that you could purchase additional permit for photography at the ticket office, so I suppose this is just a way to charge more.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/liszt_piano-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/liszt_piano-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/liszt_piano-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/liszt_piano.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> One of the most interesting exhibits at the museum: Liszt Ferenc's piano, which once belonged to Beethoven. </div> <p>The prehistoric to 11th century exhibition on the ground floor was somewhat better. The illustrations were richer, the lightings were well calibrated and had emphasis on specific items, and even the texts were no longer missing letters. As I progressed through the exhibition I began to realize that central-eastern Europe shares a similar history, up to around the end of the first millennium. The earliest settlers in the historical times were always the Celts, in both Slovenia and Hungary. Around the beginning of the first millennium the region was incorporated into the Roman empire and thus received Roman influence. In Ljubljana, one could still see the (restored) Trajan column, as well as the Roman stone tablet relic in the national museum. As the Roman empire faded, this region was then subject to Barbarian invasions, or in a more civilized name, the migration period. Starting in the 4th century, due to the pressure of the Huns (and other nomadic tribes such as Avars) from east Europe, Germanic tribes migrated westwards and occupied the region. These tribes then migrated (or pushed) further westwards, establishing the Frank kingdoms, leaving Czech, Slovakia and Slovenia to the Slavs, and later, Hungary to the Magyars. The battle between forces such as Frankish kingdom, Byzantine, and Bulgaria, can often be seen in central-eastern Europe during this time period. Residents from these regions were mostly Christianized by the end of the first Millennium, and what happened afterwards is really more easily analyzed in the framework of Medieval feudal systems. In the early second millennium, modern day Hungary, Czechia and Slovakia were ruled by native monarchs, such as Saint Stephen (Szent Istvan) in Hungary, or duchy of Bohemia in Czechia. Despite ruled by native monarchs, these monarchs all identified themselves with the western Catholic Christianity, esp. after the Great Schism. Modern day Slovenia was mostly absorbed into the Holy Roman Empire early on, and the entire central-eastern Europe fell under the direct rule of House of Luxembourg starting the 14th century. Charles IV, initially possessing the crown of Bohemia, rose to prominent position and acquired the throne of the Holy Roman Empire, with his seat in modern day Prague. Later, Sigismund of Luxembourg, first King of Hungary, was crowned Emperor of the Holy Roman Empire with his seats probably in nowadays Budapest. After that the house of Luxembourg gave way to the austrian House of Habsburg, and so on so forth.</p> <p>Another interesting observation was that along my journey, Budapest was the only place where I was denied reduced fee tickets at museums because I am not a citizen of EU. One does not only need to be a student/young person and a resident in Europe, but also need to be a citizen of EU in order to be considered for fee reduction. The staff at the ticket office even checked my nationality on the residence permit and said I was not eligible when I visited the national gallery in Buda castle on my second day in Budapest. As a result, I paid for ~6500 HUF (equiv. ~16 euro) for the national museum and the national gallery altogether. Considering the items and the mediocre curating, the 20 euro ticket for the Uffizi museum seems a real bargain.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market1-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market1-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market1-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market3-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market3-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market3-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm-4"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market2-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market2-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market2-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/budapest_market2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The Budapest central market, although being quite touristic, was my happy place. </div> <p>I also tried out other touristic experiences in Budapest. On the first day I boarded an evening cruise along the Danube, and took photos of Buda castle, the Parliament, and many other magnificent architecture along the Danube with shiny lights in the evening. Retrospectively, the cold wind on the Danube probably weakened my immune system and indirectly led to me being ill for the next three days. On the second day I took a walk on the Buda hill, and found that the Citadella as well as the monument were closed due to restoration. The construction site was like a normal one, and it was hard to believe it was a historical architecture covered by the scaffold. I did, however, had an interesting experience on the path near the top of the hill. A local guy, about 50-60 years of age, was there running a gambling stall. He had three bottle caps, and a small ball under one of them. The rule was quite simple. He put the ball under one cap and quickly mix the caps like a magician, and he would ask passers-by where the ball was. The wager was always 100 euro or equivalence, and if the person guessed correctly, he would get another 100 euro. It was unbelieveable that people would really fall for that, as not only was it obvious that as long as the owner was a good enough magician, the expectation would be -33 euro per attempt, but the wager was also high and the so was the risk. However, under my watch, three tourists of the same age happily threw in around four to five hundred euro and lost around half of it, whether because of the showmanship of the owner, the good mood of the tourists, or simply because they were so wealthy that they didn’t care about several hundred bucks.</p> <div class="row justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-12"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/parliament-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/parliament-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/central_europe/parliament-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/central_europe/parliament.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" data-zoomable="" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Can't miss out on the touristic events: taking an evening cruise on Danube and take photos of the parliament. </div> <p>In the evening I went to the Chinatown in Budapest, and experienced how rapidly the quality of the infrastructure and constructions declined away from the center. Only 3km from the central business district and I no longer felt I was in the splendid capital of Hungary, and when I reached Chinatown, circa 5km from the center, it was almost like I came to an post-apocalyptic abandoned wholesale market. This property reminded me of Beijing, although the scale is different. 5-10km from the CBD, Beijing already felt more like a mediocre city rather than a capital. And if you go another 5-10km from places like Haidian district, as you enter the mountains, the infrastructure of the city completely declines to that of a county. In contrast, when you are in Shanghai, you find plenty of secondary city centers that make areas 10 or 20km from the primary city center up to the same quality level of infrastructure, if not even higher. I observed similar conditions in Prague, arguably my favorite city along my journey, where you can easily go 5km and stay in the prosperous and well-maintained urban areas - I am not talking about concrete jungles, but clean and tidy streets, cute buildings, etc.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Travel"/><category term="Hungary"/><category term="Budapest"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In between the Germans and the Slavs, the Hungarian capital offers a different flavour.]]></summary></entry></feed>